So today's דף daf is כח Chaf Ches and we begin with
the bottom of כז Chaf Zayin עמוד ב. Amud Beis. You'll remember,
it got erased. Anyway, we had a whole fun time yesterday interpreting
the פסוקים psukim in the beginning of ויקרא Vayikra to show that
the הפשט Hefshet and ניתוח, Nituach, the flaying and the dismembering, it's
actually פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim which shows what the רבנים
Rabbanim were teaching us, does not require a כהן. Kohen. So the
גמרא Gemara figured out which exact פסוק psuk it decided was extra
to teach us that. Then we focused on עמוד ב Amud Beis
on a statement of Rav Assi in the name of Rabbi Yochanan
that said if a non-כהן Kohen actually arranged the woodpile, he's חייב
מיתה. chayav misa. It's an עבודה avodah that you're חייב מיתה chayav
misa for. Now, and the גמרא, Gemara, now I want to remind
you by the way there are עבודות avodos that a non-כהן Kohen
is not allowed to do that he's not חייב מיתה. chayav misa.
We learned before, remember, about תרומת הדשן, terumas hadeshen, is it only
putting something on, is it taking something off, is it עבודה תמה,
avodah tamah, a final stage not an interim stage? So saying you're
חייב מיתה chayav misa is pretty radical. A, you're saying that a
כהן Kohen has to do it, which is פשט pshat of the
פסוק, psuk, and B, you're saying that it's considered like one of
these real final עבודות avodos and you're חייב מיתה. chayav misa. The
גמרא, Gemara, although it's פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim וערכו בני
אהרן הכהנים את הנתחים, V'archu Bnei Aharon Hakohanim es hanetachim, no that's
the נתחים, netachim, but anyway that they that they order the anyway
the whatever the פסוק psuk is, they order the fire, they put
wood on the fire, וערכו עצים על האש, V'archu etzim al ha'esh,
so anyway although it's the פסוק, psuk, the גמרא Gemara challenged it.
Rav Zeira challenged it and he said it's a nighttime עבודה. avodah.
A זר zar should not be invalid for a nighttime עבודה. avodah.
Shocking! Not only are you not חייב מיתה, chayav misa, זר zar
should not be invalid even though the פסוק psuk says בני אהרן.
Bnei Aharon. And the גמרא Gemara basically accepted the answer. And the
גמרא Gemara basically said okay you're right, we're not talking about the
ordering of the wood, we're talking about putting the new wood. Putting
the new wood is something that the גמרא Gemara claimed, although again
it's found in some other sources that that happened before daybreak, it
sounded like putting the new wood was at the גמרא Gemara claimed
putting the new wood happened after daybreak and that would be the
only thing you'd be חייב מיתה chayav misa for. But basically you're
right, if it's a night עבודה, avodah, it's not חייב מיתה chayav
misa and maybe even a non-כהן Kohen can do it and the
תרומת הדשן terumas hadeshen although it's in the night technically it's a
day עבודה avodah and the גמרא Gemara completely sort of changed that
statement of Rav Zeira, of what do you call it, of Rabbi
Yochanan and basically in you know almost you know in defiance of
the of the simple sense of the פסוקים. psukim. And then it
ended with a question about whether you do a lottery for certain
things or not. So now we pick up at the bottom of
כז Chaf Zayin עמוד ב Amud Beis with like a repeat of
the סוגיא sugya but with a different sort of orientation. Let's take
a look. So two lines from the bottom of כז Chaf Zayin
עמוד ב. Amud Beis. איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri others say, מתקיף
לה matzkif lah Rav Zeira, Rav Zeira's challenge to this idea of
arranging the woodpile that a זר zar is חייב מיתה chayav misa
was not from the fact that it was a night עבודה. avodah.
Here's his challenge: וכי יש לך עבודה שיש אחריה עבודה פסולה בזר?
vechi yesh lach avodah sheyesh achareiha avodah psula b'zar? Here's his challenge.
This already is something we're familiar with. Do you have an interim
עבודה avodah that is invalid with a זר? zar? Because remember as
we learned before עבודת תם, avodas tam, right, ועבדתם, v'avodatem,
עבודה תמה, avodah tamah, only a final עבודה avodah not an interim
עבודה avodah are you חייב מיתה chayav misa for a זר. zar.
So here would you have an interim עבודה avodah that's invalid and
this is interim because you're arranging the woodpile in order to put
on the wood? It's not a final עבודה. avodah. Now again that's
fine to say you're not חייב מיתה chayav misa and that's enough
to challenge Rabbi Yochanan. Rabbi Yochanan said you're חייב מיתה. chayav misa.
But again the challenge seems a little extreme. He says like it's
not invalid with a non-כהן, Kohen, even a non-כהן Kohen can even
do it, which again is quite radical. But that's his challenge now.
Not that it's a night עבודה, avodah, but that it's an interim
עבודה, avodah, the arranging of the wood on the woodpile. So now
the גמרא Gemara pushes back.
והרי אברים ופדרים. ve-harei avarim u'fedarim. What about the the limbs and
the fats? Now what type of question is that? That's not an
interim עבודה, avodah, that's the last thing you do with a קרבן
korban is you burn the limbs and the fats. So that was
a question before when the challenge was a night עבודה. avodah. So
we said the burning of the limbs happens at night. But it's
not a night but sure that's not the issue. The issue is
an interim עבודה avodah and that's not relevant here. So Rashi basically
says that two-thirds of the next סוגיא sugya until the until the
end of the פרק perek is all essentially an accidental copy over
from the previous סוגיא. sugya. That we're going to go through the
same questions but they're completely irrelevant here. And actually he cuts them
out of the גירסא. girsa. He says it was a mistake in
copy because you know it's a different approach, so they just oh
great let's cut and paste the earlier questions and answers, but the
earlier questions and answers don't work because it's a different question, it's
a different assumption. This huge Tosfos here on כז Chaf Zayin עמוד
ב Amud Beis tries to fit in this גירסא girsa with the
new assumption. Okay and he does amazing somersaults to have it make
sense. But for our sake we will presume like Rashi that it
is a mistaken copy over so I'll read it through but you'll
see obviously why it doesn't make
sense. Okay? So he's only so he's only economizing on this so
why would they put something that doesn't make sense? No it was
a at what stage
did it get incorrectly copied? it just got sort of copied over.
He's not claiming that the גמרא Gemara intentionally did it. רש״י Rashi
actually cuts it out of the גירסא. girsa. Look at the first
look at the first word of רש״י. Rashi. והרי ואמרו פדרים לא
גרסינן לכולה הך גירסא דאיברים ודתרומת הדשן השתא דאמרינן לגבי ve-harei ve-amru
pedarim lo garsinan le-chula hach girsa de-eivarim ve-di-trumas hadeshen hashta de-amrinan legabei
et cetera, et cetera. Because it's all not relevant. The question here
is about interim עבודה, avodah, not night time עבודה. avodah. So let's
read through it. It'll be a little repeat of yesterday but it
won't make sense now.
Is רש״י Rashi saying actually that this got in here because the
scribe was working too quickly?
Who knows why he's saying ואגב שיטפא דריהטא דגרסא? ve-agav shitpa deriheta
de-girsa?
Right. Yeah. Yeah. Unbelievable.
Well again, whose mistake was it? Was it the mistake in the
scribe? Was it a mistake at an oral stage when it was
being told over?
But somehow, right, exactly. Because you're exactly as Dov says,
you're by by the rush of the you know the rush of
the telling it over, you go through, you repeat the same questions
again and you don't stop to think that they're not relevant here.
Yeah, yeah, there's another way of asking the question, not about night,
about interim עבודה. avodah. Oh, so then it says back and forth
this thing about איברים ופדרים, eivarim u-fedarim, thing about תרומת הדשן. trumas
ha-deshen. Nobody stops to say, one minute, none of that makes sense
now for your
question at year 500 and 1100 where it was being copied. All
right, anyway.
So let's take a look. והרי... ve-harei...
okay. והרי איברים ופדרים, ve-harei eivarim u-fedarim, so again, the question is
how could an interim עבודה, avodah, the organizing of the wood, be
something that a זר zar is חייב מיתה? chayav misah? So the
גמרא Gemara says, why not? What about the fact and the limbs?
Again, that's not an interim עבודה, avodah, but that is relevant to
the night question because it is a night עבודה. avodah. סוף עבודת
יממא היא. sof avodas yemama hee. And again, the answer has to
do with day or night. Oh, that's actually not a night עבודה,
avodah, that's ending of the עבודה avodah of the day. Of course
that's completely again irrelevant to the question about interim versus final עבודה.
avodah. והרי תרומת הדשן, ve-harei trumas ha-deshen, how about the taking of
the ashes? Again, good question if the issue is a night עבודה
avodah because that seems to be a night עבודה. avodah. Not relevant
if it's about an interim עבודה. avodah. תרומת הדשן trumas ha-deshen is
not an interim עבודה. avodah. It's the end of a process. Again,
bad question here. תחלת עבודת יממא היא. techilas avodas yemama hee. Oh,
that's the beginning of the day עבודה. avodah. Again, good answer if
the question is night versus day. It's a day עבודה, avodah, not
relevant if the question is interim versus final
עבודה. avodah. Okay? דאמר רבי יוחנן קידש ידיו לתרומת הדשן למחר אינו
צריך לקדש שכבר קידש מתחלת עבודה de-amar Rebbe Yochanan kideish yadav li-trumas
ha-deshen le-machar eino tzarich le-kadesh she-kvar kideish mi-techilas avodah because you already
sanctified your hands from the beginning of the עבודה. avodah. This is
the beginning of the עבודה avodah of the day. אלא קשיא, ela
kashya, but now we've got a problem. Again, presumably a problem is
that the challenge that it's an interim עבודה. avodah. Forget this back
and forth we just had. What about the fact that it's an
interim עבודה, avodah, the organizing of the wood? How could you be
חייב מיתה chayav misah on it? Okay? And remember, again, I'm not
sure a זר zar should be okay for it, but you shouldn't
be חייב מיתה, chayav misah, that's the issue before עבודה תמה. avodah
tamah. So אלא אי איתמר הכי
איתמר, ela ee itmar hachi itmar, here's what was said. So we
have to reframe this idea of the woodpile חייב מיתה chayav misah
because it's an interim עבודה. avodah. So here's what he said. אמר
רב אשי אמר רבי יוחנן זר שסידר שני גזירי עצים חייב, amar
Rav Ashi amar Rebbe Yochanan zar she-sidar shenei gezeirei eitzim chayav,
not organizing the woodpile, but putting the two logs of wood on
the woodpile afterwards. That's where you're חייב. chayav. הואיל ועבודה תמה היא,
ho'il ve-avodah tamah hee, and here it has that phrase עבודה תמה.
avodah tamah. That is the end of a process. After organizing the
wood, you put on the two logs of the wood.
Okay? השלמת עבודה. hashlamas avodah.
Okay, you could say that, but you know you could also say,
תוספות Tosafos said, you could say the blood is preparatory for the
burning of the limbs. You know, at least it is the end
of the wood process. Okay? It's the end of dealing with the
fire. But yes, it is possible to say otherwise, and that's רש״י
Rashi himself said, if you remember this was not listed in the
earlier list of things that are עבודה תמה avodah tamah that a
זר zar is חייב. chayav. And that exact debate would be what
Michael is saying. Do you view this as the end because it's
the end of preparing the fire, or is it interim because you're
going to burn the limbs on it and this is just to
prepare it to burning the limbs, burning the parts of the קרבן,
korban, the fat and the limbs and so on. So this is
saying that no, at least the logs is an עבודה תמה, avodah
tamah, you're חייב. chayav. Okay? And we're not concerned now about the
idea of a night versus day, we're just concerned about עבודה תמה.
avodah tamah. So מתקיף לה רבא, maskif lah Rava, so רבא Rava
says, אלא מעתה תיבעי פייס, ela me-atah tiba'i payis,
if it is so important that it is an עבודה תמה avodah
tamah and that a זר zar is חייב chayav for it, so
why not have a, why not have a lottery for it? Similar
to how we the discussion continued yesterday after we decided you're חייב
מיתה, chayav misah, the question becomes let's have a פייס, payis, a
lottery. So the גמרא Gemara says, ולא בעי פייס? ve-lo ba'ei payis?
Does it not require a lottery? והתניא, ve-hatanya, but isn't it taught
in a ברייתא, braisa, מי שזכה בתרומת הדשן יזכה בסידור שני גזירי
עצים, mi she-zachah bi-trumas ha-deshen yizkeh bi-siddur shenei gezeirei eitzim, the one
who got the removing of the ashes gets the putting of the
logs? So it's part of that lottery. The גמרא, Gemara, it's interesting,
yesterday the גמרא Gemara said רב Rav forgot this ברייתא, braisa, here
it's just to say challenging him with the ברייתא. braisa. And now
the גמרא Gemara here comes and defends רבא. Rava. הכי קאמר. Hachi
ka'amar. No, no, here's what רבא Rava meant. יפיסו בה בפני עצמה.
Yipaisu ba bifnei atzma. If it's so important that you're חייב מיתה
chayav misa and it's an עבודה תמה, avoda tama, it should get
its own lottery.
Now, of course we had that before too.
So the גמרא Gemara says כדאמרינן למימרא דעבודה תמה וזר. k'de'amrinan lemaimra
d'avoda tama v'zar. Okay. So now כדאמרינן. k'de'amrinan. אלא כדאמרינן, Ela k'de'amrinan,
like we said. Now, it's not clear what's like we said. How
does it, what's the answer to that? But anyway, let's now the
גמרא Gemara now the גמרא Gemara
unpacks. First of all תוספות Tosfos asks anyway. תוספות Tosfos says, I
don't understand, so many things that were שלעפט schlepped along with the
lottery of the תמיד Tamid are things you'd be
חייב מיתה chayav misa and is עבודה תמה avoda tama and there
was one פיס payis for thirteen jobs, so who knows what, who
knows? It's a very difficult סוגיא. suggya. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says
למימרא, lemeimra, the fact that רבא Rava said let it get its
own lottery
suggests, implies עבודה תמה וזר חייב עליה מיתה פייס פייס, avoda tama
v'zar chayav aleha misa payis payis, that something that is an עבודה
תמה avoda tama and therefore a non-כהן kohen gets מיתה misa would
demand its own lottery. That's רבא Rava's question. Okay. אין זר חייב
עליה מיתה לא בעי פייס. Ein zar chayav aleha misa lo bayei
payis. If not, it does not
get its own lottery. Is that really true? והרי שחיטה. v'harei shechita.
How about שחיטה? shechita? That gets its own lottery. Okay. And that,
that does not get its own lottery and that is an עבודה
avoda that a, I'm sorry, let's do that again. שחיטה shechita a
זר zar is not invalid for. And שחיטה shechita does get its
own lottery because the first of the thirteen that we do for
the תמיד, Tamid, the first one is who gets to shecht. So
if anything is considered to be the one that fundamentally you're doing
the lottery for, it's for the שחיטה. shechita. But the שחיטה shechita
a זר zar can do. And רבא Rava's assuming that the only
thing that gets a lottery is something that a זר zar cannot
do. והרי שחיטה? v'harei shechita? No, שאני שחיטה דתחלת עבודה דיממא היא.
shani shechita de-chilvas avoda d'yama hi. Again, this phrase, the beginning of
the day עבודה, avoda, but here what it means is because it's
part of all these other עבודות avodas that a זר zar is
חייב מיתה chayav misa for. So since there are so many עבודות
avodas related to the תמיד Tamid that a זר zar cannot do
and a זר zar is חייב, chayav, that's why there's a lottery
for all the עבודות avodas of the תמיד. Tamid. But רבא Rava's
question was that there's no lottery for
this, so the fact that שחיטה shechita isn't the problem. But why,
says רבא, Rava, is there not a lottery for the actual putting
of the wood by itself? That deserves its independent lottery. Again, it's
a strange question because as I just said, you've explained why שחיטה
shechita is part of the lottery, but according to רבא, Rava, so
many things related to the תמיד Tamid should all be getting their
own lottery if you want the wood to get its own lottery.
So again, it's not very clear what the question is, what the
answer is. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara goes back and says
like this. למימרא, lemeimra, this suggests עבודה תמה בעי פייס, avoda tama
bayei payis, עבודה שאחר עבודה לא בעי פייס. avoda she-achar avoda lo
bayei payis. Now again, this seems to be at least until now,
although there was questions we had on it, you understood how it
was relating to the issue at hand. Now we're back to something
that seems to be a just an again a copyover from yesterday's
סוגיא suggya that doesn't make sense. Okay, because let's see why. This
seems to say from רבא Rava's question that an end עבודה avoda
needs a פיס. payis. עבודה שאחר עבודה לא בעי פייס, avoda she-achar
avoda lo bayei payis, an interim עבודה avoda does not need a
פיס, payis, that's our emphasis now. End עבודה avoda versus interim עבודה.
avoda. So one minute, והרי איברים ופדרים. v'harei eivar mukdarim. What about
the limbs, which presumably
get
don't get... well, the question is, but before the question of the
limbs was that it was a night עבודה avoda and that they
did have their own פיס. payis. So presumably the point is here
they do have their פיס, payis, who brings the איברים eivarim to
the top of the כבש? kevesh? So why is that true? Why
do they get their פיס? payis? Now again, the question is, why
is that a problem? The איברים eivarim are עבודה תמה, avoda tama,
they're the end of, they're an end עבודה, avoda, they're putting it
on the fire. So wait, wait, wait, the question was before yesterday,
why do the איברים eivarim get a פיס? payis? They're a night
עבודה. avoda. And the answer was no, no, no, they're part of
the day עבודה, avoda, which is the answer. סוף עבודה דיממא היא.
sof avoda d'yama hi. That's the next answer here. So that was
a question when the issue was night versus day. Ah, the איברים
eivarim are a night עבודה, avoda, why do they get a פיס?
payis? Answer, they're a day עבודה. avoda. But here the issue is
end versus interim. And again, it's not relevant. The איברים eivarim are
an end עבודה. avoda. And so again, this is an accidental copy
according to רש"י, Rashi, copyover from before. Let's just see it again.
והרי תרומת הדשן. v'harei trumas hadeshen. What about תרומת הדשן? trumas hadeshen?
Again, if the question was a night עבודה, avoda, you'd understand. It's
a night עבודה. avoda. Why does it get a פיס? payis? And
the answer is משום מעשה שהיה, mishum ma'aseh she-haya, because of the
story, the guy got pushed over and so on. If the issue
is interim versus end עבודה, avoda, again it doesn't make sense. תרומת
הדשן trumas hadeshen is an end עבודה. avoda. So what's the issue?
Okay. So again, major sections here about the questioning about the איברים
eivarim and the תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen are according to רש"י Rashi
are all copied over. They were all about day versus night, the
answers were all about day versus night, they're completely irrelevant to our
concern right now which is the issue of עבודה תמה. avoda tama.
טוב, Tov, יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
Why, I don't understand why bringing the איברים eivarim and the פדר
pader onto the כבש kevesh is a עבודה תמה? avoda tama? Isn't
it a...
no, no, no, it's the הקרבה hakrava of them.
It's the הקרבה. hakrava. Yeah.
So they did get a פיס payis though, remember there was a
final פיס payis for who brings
it onto
the
altar.
category of עבודת תמיד Avodat Tamid or interim—right,
right, so a זר zar who brought the stuff to the כבש
kevesh actually would not be חייב. chayav. That's true. Okay, but the
issue here about who gets a פיס payis and it was complicated
anyway yesterday, but it's certainly here problem that it's all introducing the
issue about the questions and answers aren't relevant. The questions and answers
are about night versus day. At the end of the day what
we're saying is—just to focus us on the
conclusion—yesterday we were saying that a night עבודה, avodah, a זר zar
could not be חייב מיתה, chayav misa, maybe even it's כשירה בזר,
ksheira bezar, which again is a shocker based on the פסוקים. psukim.
But that emphasis of night versus day and having to say that
certain things like the wood being put on the fire actually took
place in the day, not the night, okay, and calling certain things
like the תרומת הדשן trumat hadeshen a day עבודה. avodah. So yesterday
we insisted that it be a day עבודה avodah for a זר
zar to be חייב. chayav. Here we're saying something that we said
a week ago, which is that only in an עבודת תמיד avodat
tamid a זר zar is חייב chayav and we're discussing the wood
pile and is arranging the wood is not an עבודת תמיד, avodat
tamid, putting the logs on the wood maybe is, maybe isn't. It's
the end of the wood pile עבודה, avodah, but it's not the
end of the whole process which is the burning of the limbs.
But that at least is a concept that we are familiar with,
that of עבודת תמיד. avodat tamid. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
concludes with this—and then all these issues about who exactly gets a
פיס payis and what criteria get a—do you use to determine if
you get a פיס payis or not. אמר מר. Amar mar. אמר
מר זוטרא ואי תימא רב אשי, Amar Mar Zutra ve'isema Rav Ashi,
אף אנן נמי תנינא, af anan nami tenina, we also taught. אמר
להם הממונה, Amar lahem hamemuneh, צאו וראו אם הגיע זמן השחיטה, tze'u
ur'u im higia zman hashchita, go see if the time for שחיטה
shchita has come. ואילו זמן סידור גזרי עצים לא תני. Ve'ilu zman
sidur gizrei eitzim lo tani. But it doesn't say the time of
the burning of the wood. So what does that prove? So you
remember yesterday that proved that it was a night עבודה avodah and
it was a question: How can you say the wood was put
on in the day and it's a day עבודה? avodah? It says
they waited until it gets light to do the שחיטה, shchita, right?
And they didn't wait as though—so not to put on the wood.
So it shows that the wood was done at night. And what
was the answer? The answer was הכא דאית ליה תקנתא תני הכא
דלית ליה תקנתא לא תני. hacha d'it lei takanta tani hacha d'leit
lei takanta lo tani. No, no, no, no, they waited till it
got light to do the wood also, but they didn't wait for
the announcement because most—you know—they basically knew when it was light or
not. So they were only super careful not to שחט shecht the
קרבן korban too soon, because then you'd have to—you know—burn the whole
קרבן, korban, you'd have to get rid of it, you'd lose a
whole animal. But they weren't super careful about the wood because if
they made a mistake, fine, they'll take it off and put it
back on again. But really, that's what the גמרא Gemara said yesterday,
it's the exact same discussion, that was to make the claim that
the wood was done in the—to challenge the idea that the wood
was done in the day, it looks like it's done at the
night, and the answer is no, no, no, it really was done
in the day. Here, however, it seems to be saying something else.
Here it seems to be being brought to try to support an
argument. What argument are you supporting by trying to show that it
was done at night? So look at רש״י. Rashi. רש״י Rashi says:
אף אנן נמי תנינא af anan nami tenina about eight lines before
the end of the פרק. perek. דסידור גזרי עבודת תמיד היא. Desidur
gizrei avodat tamid hee.
We're trying to prove from this idea that it sounds like the
wood was done at night to prove that it's an עבודת תמיד.
avodat tamid. Why is that a proof? לרבי יוחנן ולא כרבי יהושע
בן לוי דלא מנו לה בעבודה שזר חייב עליה משום דיש אחר
סידור אברים—I LeRabbi Yochanan velo keRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi d'lo manu la
be'avoda shezar chayav aleha mishum d'yesh achar sidur evarim just skipped to
the next רש״י—ואילו שני גזרי עצים לא תני אלמא עבודת לילה היא
והוא גמר סידור מערכה.
The fact that we're showing that it was done at night because
they didn't wait for the announcement to do it, you see it
was done at night, that makes it an עבודת תמיד, avodat tamid,
because the night עבודות avodas are done and the burning of the
limbs is done in the day. So meaning, according to רש״י, Rashi
this at least this last line is can be used for our
discussion not about night versus day, but night versus day is relevant
for our discussion—is it an עבודת תמיד? avodat tamid? Is it an
end עבודה? avodah? Right? Do you understand that? Because if it was
done in the day, then you could say, 'Oh, you put the
logs in the day, you're not yet done, you're going to burn
the limbs.' But if the logs are done at night, oh, so
the night עבודות avodas are getting the fire ready and the day
עבודות avodas are burning the limbs, and therefore the putting of the
logs is the end of the עבודה avodah of the fire—of the
wood pile—because that is ended at the end of the night. And
the fire is a night thing, and the limbs are the day
thing, and therefore it's the end of a process and therefore it's
עבודת תמיד. avodat tamid. And you're חייב מיתה. chayav misa. And the
גמרא Gemara at the end says, maybe not, maybe really it would
be a day עבודה, avodah, they just didn't wait for the announcement.
Even if it's at night.
So yes, thank you for pointing that out. This סוגיא sugya argues
with the previous. So at the end of the day,
there's two debates. One debate is technically the back and forth here
at the end, was the wood done at night, which is what
it sounds like, or do we try to say, no, no, no,
it was done at day, they just didn't wait for the announcement.
So when was the wood done? Okay, but yes, the other debate
is, are you חייב chayav to—a זר zar be חייב מיתה chayav
misa for an עבודה avodah of night? This סוגיא sugya assumes yes,
let it be a night עבודה, avodah, זר zar is חייב מיתה.
chayav misa. The only issue is: is it an עבודת תמיד? avodat
tamid? And it is. עבודת תמם avodat tamam because it was done
at night and that ended the process, whereas yesterday's סוגיא sugya assumed
you needed it to be a day עבודה avoda for a זר
zar to be חייב מיתה. chayav misah. So and that was a
new criteria we had never heard that before. Okay, so that is
the basic debate between these two approaches, the copied over text notwithstanding.
הדרן לך בראשונה. Hadran lach barishona. And now we thankfully enter a
new פרק perek which is going to be a much more, at
least the opening is going to be a lot easier. So let's
take a look. אמר להם הממונה. Amar lahem hamemuna.
Now this will sound familiar because this is a lot of what
we were quoting before or alluding to before. So we're back to
remember they did the whole פיס, payas, they did the whole drawing
of the lots. It said they שחט shechted it, they brought the
limbs to the ramp, they went from the ramp to the top,
we're talking about the normal עבודות avodas they would do in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, but now we doubled back because we
talked about which how the lots were drawn, but now we're going
to double back to talk about actually when they began the עבודה
avoda to do the שחיטה shechita and the bringing of the תמיד.
tamid. Okay, so let's take a look. אמר להם הממונה, Amar lahem
hamemuna, the appointed person said when they were getting ready to bring
to do the שחיטה shechita and to bring the תמיד: tamid: צאו
וראו אם הגיע זמן השחיטה. Tzu u'reu im higia zman ha'shechita. That's
just what we quoted a minute ago. Go see if the time
for שחיטה's shechita come, go see if it's daybreak yet. אם
הגיע, Im higia, if the time of שחיטה shechita had arrived, it
was daybreak, הרואה אומר ברקאי, haroeh omer barkai, the רואה roeh would
say ברקאי, barkai, which basically means the morning has burst forth or
brightness. So מתיא בן שמואל אומר, Masya ben Shmuel omer, and מתיא
בן שמואל Masya ben Shmuel says that he presumably he says that
he would say, האיר פני כל המזרח עד שבחברון. He'ir pnei kol
hamizrach ad sheb'Hevron. Now if it's again the גמרא's Gemara going to
unpack exactly who's saying what, but it sounds like in the משנה
Mishnah that they would ask him after
did it get light off the east, is the east light all
the way to חברון? Hevron? Like can you see the light reaching
all the way to חברון? Hevron? זה אומר הין Zu omer hein
and he said yes. What?
If it's the east it's in ירושלים? Yerushalayim?
South. It's to the south.
Well maybe that's therefore how far why it has to get it
has to be lighter so that the light reaches all the way
around to the south.
That's a good point. Someone standing up on some
so thank you רש"י Rashi says he's on a roof, he's on
a wall, he's somewhere high, he's looking to seeing if there's been
if the guy
below telling the רואה roeh go up and take a look. He
goes to the standing
exactly, exactly, yes thank you I didn't mention that. He is on
a height. Okay, ולמה הוצרכו לכך, v'lama hutzru l'kach,
why did they need couldn't you tell is it day or night?
Why did they need somebody to be on the top of the
roof telling them if it's light or not? שפעם אחת עלה מאור
הלבנה, shepa'am achas ala ma'or hal'vana, because one time there was some
moonlight coming out, ודמו שהיא אור מזרח u'dimu shehi or mizrach and
it looked like it was the eastern light of the day. ושחטו
את התמיד והוציאו לבית השריפה V'shachtu es hatamid v'hotzi'u l'beis hasreifah then
they שחט shechted the תמיד tamid and then they had to burn
it outside they had to, they didn't on the altar, they had
to burn they had to destroy it because it was a פסול.
pasul. So this is what the גמרא Gemara referred to before as,
it's לית ליה תקנתא lays lay takanta you're going to have to
you're going to have to destroy the קרבן korban if you שחט
shechted it early. Okay, so that was how they knew that it
was time to begin the morning service, the guy said האיר פני
כל המזרח He'ir pnei kol hamizrach or ברקאי. barkai. And now without
sort of abruptly we switch back to the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
הורידו כהן גדול לבית הטבילה. Horidu Kohen Gadol l'beis hatvilah. Then they
got the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol go to the בית הטבילה. beis
hatvilah. Okay now again what's abrupt here is that it sounded like
we were talking about the normal service on a normal day. We're
done talking about this a normal thing the lotteries, they waited until
they knew it was the time for the שחיטה, shechita, and now
without even taking even one word of transition we go back to
יום כיפור Yom Kippur and say what they would do with the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol they'd make him go down. So it's a
little funny here. Now maybe you could say that this happened after
this אמר להם הממונה amar lahem hamemuna this whole exchange was happening
the morning of יום כיפור Yom Kippur as well. It's true it
would happen every single day, but maybe the this פרק perek is
introducing this as here's what happened also on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
So it's not clear whether the first part of this משנה Mishnah
is wrapping up our earlier discussion or should be read connected to
the second part and this is the beginning of the first day
of the beginning of the day on יום כיפור Yom Kippur itself.
Yes this was a regular thing but here's what happened also on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay not the lottery but this had definitely
and this happened on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay so they brought
the the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to the place where he would
go to the מקוה. mikvah. זה הכלל, Zeh haklal, this is the
ruling, זה הכלל היה במקדש, zeh haklal haya b'Mikdash, this is the
general principle in the מקדש. Mikdash. כל המסיך את רגליו, Kol hamesich
es raglav, anybody that went like a bowel movement, so that's the
phrase מסיך את רגליו, mesich es raglav, רש"י Rashi does מסיך mesich
means to bend over because you bend over when you're having a
bowel movement, טעון טבילה, te'un tvilah, you'd have to go into the
מקוה. mikvah. וכל המסיך מים, V'kol hamesich mayim, and if you urinated,
טעון קידוש ידיים ורגליים te'un kiddush yadayim v'raglayim then afterwards you'd have
to wash your hands and feet. Now we're not necessarily saying the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol had a bowel movement, but since we're talking
about the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol starts his day with a טבילה
tvilah we're also going back again there's always this conversation between what
you did on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and what you would regularly
do. Okay so we had a whole discussion about what you would
regularly do on a normal day and now we get back to
the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Now we say he went
to the
מקוה. mikvah. But the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would start his day
going to the מקוה. Mikvah. Okay, so now let's see in the
גמרא. Gemara. I do want to, by the way, remind you that
there was an interesting debate of the ראשונים Rishonim whether the תרומת
הדשן Trumat Hadeshen on יום כיפור Yom Kippur was done by the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol or not. Everything in the day was done
by the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. There was a debate of the
ראשונים Rishonim based on ambiguity in the גמרא, Gemara, whatever, whether the
תרומת הדשן Trumat Hadeshen was done. So even though we had all
this discussion about פיס, Payis, right, you could say it was completely
irrelevant to יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but according to some אחרונים, Achronim,
ראשונים, Rishonim, it's relevant, because at least they had the lottery even
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur for who got to do the תרומת
הדשן. Trumat Hadeshen. So there is that at least, you know, again,
interesting connection between the rest of the year, the ongoing conversation between
יום כיפור Yom Kippur and what was normally done. Yes, Charlie.
The Sephardi יום כיפור Yom Kippur doesn't even mention the תרומת הדשן.
Trumat Hadeshen.
Interesting, but the Ashkenazi one does and תוספות Tosafot references it in
that discussion of whether a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would do it
or not.
Okay, good point. Quick question, קידוש ידים ורגלים, Kiddush Yadayim V'Raglayim, am
I, should I assume it's like we do it also like כח
גברא Koach Gavra that it was a כח, Koach, the vessel, the
מצלאר? Matzlar? Yeah, yeah.
I mean, yes, that's generally yes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: תניא Tanya we've done a ברייתא. Braysa. רבי ישמעאל אומר:
Rabbi Yishmael omer: ברק ברקאי. Barak Barkai. So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
says that they were and here we're going to have all these
different opinions about what the announcer would say. Okay, so he said
he would say ברק ברקאי. Barak Barkai. It's like, it's light, it's
light, a double language. רבי עקיבא אומר: Rabbi Akiva omer: עלה ברקאי.
Alah Barkai. The morning light has risen up. I don't even know
if there's a translation for the word ברקאי. Barkai. I think it's
like a juxtaposition, like it's poker sort of, you know, or ברק,
Barak, you know, is like a lightning or, you know, a flash.
So, okay, so he said the...
Yes, this was ברק Barak versus עלה ברקאי. Alah Barkai.
I know, I didn't even catch the sense to say that, yes.
So according to רש"י, Rashi, right, עלה ברקאי, Alah Barkai, the light,
the flash has risen up means it's a little lighter than just
the beginning of the light. נחומא בן אפקשיון, Nachuma ben Afakshiyon, interesting,
אומר: omer: אפרקאי בחברון. Aparkai b'Hevron. אפרקאי בחברון. Aparkai b'Hevron.
You would say it even has gotten light to חברון. Hevron. מתיא
בן שמואל
אומר, Matya ben Shmuel omer, or whatever, הממונה על הפיסות אומר HaMemuneh
al HaPayisot omer said that the guy who was over the lots.
Interesting, now we know who the הממונה Memuneh was because it wasn't
a different person, right, we had just been talking the whole last
פרק perek about the lots, and this פרק perek opened with הממונה.
HaMemuneh. So now we see the הממונה Memuneh means the guy last
פרק perek that had been running all of the lotteries, he was
the one that was in charge, makes sense, you got one guy
in charge of everything, he was the one that was in charge
of making sure that it was daylight and that they could get
started with the שחיטה. shechitah. So הממונה על הפיסות אומר, HaMemuneh al
HaPayisot omer, he would say to the guy up on the tower:
האיר פני כל המזרח עד שבחברון? He'ir pnai kol hamizrach ad sheb'Hevron?
Has it gotten light all the way until חברון Hevron and the
guy on the tower would presumably say yes.
So that's more than ברקאי בחברון.
Barkai b'Hevron. That's like the beginning of light, this is like the
whole east is lit up to the guy, some greater degree of
light. רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר: Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer: האיר
פני כל המזרח עד בחברון He'ir pnai kol hamizrach ad b'Hevron ויצאו
כל העם איש איש למלאכתו. v'yatzu kol ha'am ish ish limlachto. Has
it gotten light, lit up all the way to חברון Hevron and
everybody now is on their way to work. So the גמרא Gemara
says: אי הכי נגה ליה טובא. Iy hachi naga lei tuvei. Now
it's very light. The whole idea is to get started the day
early, so you want to make sure it's light, but you don't
want to wait to rush hour. So the גמרא Gemara says no.
לשכור
פועלים קא אמרינן. Lishkor poalim ka amrinan. We don't mean everybody's going
to work, we mean the foremen that are going out that have
to hire the workers, they go out super early because they're the
ones that kind of hire the workers and, you know, it sort
of like, you know, they would do this daily hiring of workers,
I mean it still happens now, you know, in these, you know,
what? Yeah, exactly like in Mexico, whatever, like we need ten people
to work today, so you want the workers to start first thing
in the morning, so you better be out there looking to hire
them even earlier. Okay, what?
That's what I'm talking about how it wouldn't happen on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur anymore.
Right, right. Well, right, I mean or we're talking about is it
that time of day. But again, the fact by the way that
it's הממונה על הפיסות, Memuneh al HaPayisot, I mean again, it's, you
know, it does seem that we are talking here our משנה mishna
is not specifically in the יום כיפור Yom Kippur context. This is
something they would do every day. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: אמר רב ספרא. Amar Rav Safra. So now we're talking
about being light and starting the עבודה, avodah, so we make a
very interesting shift right now, okay. צלותא דאברהם. Tzluta deAvraham. The prayer
of אברהם. Avraham. ותיקין. Vatikin.
Well, you think we're going to talk about שחרית Shacharis because אברהם
Avraham was מתקן שחרית. metaken Shacharis. צלותא דאברהם, Tzluta deAvraham, but actually
we're going to talk about מנחה. Mincha. מדימשחרי כותלי. Mi-de-mash-charey koslei. From
the time the walls get dark. Meaning if the sun is rising
and you have a wall that's facing like, you know, facing towards
the east or east-west whatever, so for the first part of the
day the wall is light, by the time the sun gets overhead,
right then it starts, it's no longer being lit by the sun
and by the time it moves over here it's actually shadow being
cast. What did I say? מנחה Mincha was
מתקן? mitakein?
יצחק Yitzchak was מתקן mitakein מנחה. Mincha. So the מהרש"א Maharsha says,
yeah יצחק Yitzchak might have been מתקן, mitakein, but he had a
מסורה mesorah from אברהם. Avraham. So but the way I really read
that is, is that he also says like אברהם Avraham was the
עיקר ikar because if you look at the אבות, Avos, who's the
one really praying all the time? Or you know, it's אברהם, Avraham,
or certainly the one in regular conversation with God. I mean although
you do have you know, by the, you do have יצחק Yitzchak
is praying to God, לנוכח אשתו, linoach ishto, that is true. But
anyway, so he says yeah we're just saying really אברהם Avraham was
מתקן mitakein all the idea of תפילה, tefilla, okay.
אברהם Avraham was דאוונינג davening שחרית, Shacharit, שחור, shachor, and יצחק Yitzchak
דאוונינג davening מנחה קטנה!
Mincha Ketana! שכוח! shkoach! That's a good answer.
Yeah, I never made this association that the word for dawn
is
blackness.
Dawn means blackness? Oh, שחר shachar and שחור, shachor, מכי משחרי, miki
mashchari, yeah. I never made that.
That's an interesting
point.
שחר, shachar, yeah, it's interesting. Okay, בוקר boker actually right is ולבקר.
ulivaker. בוקר, boker, you're talking about ברקאי בוקר. barkai boker. Right, בוקר
boker actually means daybreak because that's לבקר, levaker, that's when you distinguish
between light and darkness, right? שחרית Shacharit is actually I think later
than בוקר, boker, but it is interesting that it meant of dark,
yeah, it's interesting. Now if you look here at the side, it
quotes the ערוך Aruch who says basically what the מהרש"א Maharsha says,
I don't know if you have it in your גמרא. Gemara. In
my גמרא, Gemara, on the right hand margin, the second thing in
the small print, in the Vilna print, like of the notes, marginal
notes, עיין בערוך, ayein be’Aruch, ערך שחר, erech shachar, א, aleph, פירוש
peirush תפילת האבות כולם. tefillas haavos kullam. So ולא הזכיר אברהם, v’lo
hizkir Avraham, it really means all the אבות' Avos prayers, right? ולא
הזכיר אברהם אלא מפני שהוא עיקר בתפילה, v’lo hizkir Avraham ela mipnei
shehu ikar bitfilla, ויצא יצחק לשוח בשדה לפנות ערב, vayeitzei Yitzchak lasuach
basadeh lifnos erev, משעה שנכנס השמש במערב ובאותו עת מתחילין הכותלים שבמזרח
להשחיר וזו השיחה תפילת הצהריים כדת שמסורה לו מאביו. mishe’she’nichnas ha’shemesh ba’maarav
u’ve’oso eis matchilin hakoslim shebamizrach lehishchar ve’zu hasicha tefillas hatzorayim kedas shemesurah
lo me’aviv. Basically, so the מהרש"א Maharsha got it from much earlier,
from the ערוך. Aruch. Yeah, אברהם Avraham already was מתקן mitakein all
the תפילות, tefillos, okay. So anyway we're talking now about, interestingly about
מנחה, Mincha, but yes, Don makes an interesting point, the word שחר
shachar here is about dark, okay, is about dark, but we're talking
now about the day beginning to the sun moving to now to
the other side of the horizon.
מכי משחרי miki mashchari is until this point?
No, מכי, miki, from when, yeah. Okay, אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav
Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, אנמי מאברהם נגמור ונגמור. anami
me’Avraham negmor unigmor. What, we're going to learn from אברהם? Avraham? So
what does that question mean? So רש"י Rashi says, yeah we know
אברהם Avraham was always such a זריז zariz and he always did
things, you know, בזריזות, bizrizus, so how could we learn from אברהם?
Avraham? But by the way, this whole thing is bizarre, because we're
just making a claim, it's not like we're quoting a פסוק, passuk,
it's not like we have any evidence, look here's when אברהם Avraham
דאוונד, davened, let's learn from this event when we're going to דאוון.
daven. Okay, but anyway it seems like he's just referring to it,
he wants to call it מנחה, Mincha, so he refers to it
as אברהם's Avraham prayer, you know. But he understood it that somehow
we're learning from something from אברהם. Avraham. How could we learn from
אברהם? Avraham? So רש"י Rashi again says the challenge is that אברהם
Avraham was always זריזים zrizim and we can't learn from him. But
if you look at the side, at the previous marginal notes, it
makes a, again quoting the ערוך, Aruch, it makes a much more
significant interpretation of this גמרא. Gemara. ובערוך פירש, uve’Aruch peirush, היכא נלמד
מאברהם, heicha nilmad me’Avraham, קיים
התורה עד שלא ניתנה, kiyem haTorah ad shelo nitnah, ואין לנו ללמוד
אלא ממנהג נביאים מפני שנהגו בהלכה למשה מסיני. ve’ein lanu lilmod ela
miminhag nevi'im mipnei shenahagu behalacha leMoshe miSinai. How can you learn from
anything prior to מתן תורה? Matan Torah? That's actually this גמרא Gemara
we're going to say the famous teaching that also appears elsewhere, but
the famous teaching that the אבות Avos were מקיים כל התורה כולה
mekayem kol haTorah kulla is going to be later in the דף.
daf. But the way the
ערוך Aruch reads this challenge is like okay, it's very nice to
say they were מקיים כל התורה כולה. mekayem kol haTorah kulla. Let's
say they were. But they were doing it on their own. So
that doesn't teach you הלכה. halacha. הלכה halacha is only when you're
starting to do it as a matter of law, and you can't
learn any actual הלכה halacha from what אברהם Avraham did. Quite fascinating,
you know, because it's also like an interesting question. Do we learn
the הלכות halachos of, you know, of ברית מילה, bris milah, is
the ציווי tzivui of ברית מילה bris milah that's the basic הלכה
halacha of ברית מילה, bris milah, the commandment to אברהם, Avraham, or
much later, right, in ויקרא Vayikra where it says וביום השמיני ימול
בשר ערלתו. ubayom hashmini yimol basar orlato. You read the רמב"ם, Rambam,
and the רמב"ם Rambam basically says, you know, until נח Noach was
given seven מצוות. mitzvos. Came אברהם Avraham and he was given ברית
מילה bris milah and he was מתקן שחרית. mitakein Shacharis. And came
יצחק Yitzchak and he was מתקן, mitakein, you know, מנחה Mincha and
he was
מתקן—no, mitakein I think he says no, מנחה. Mincha. And then the
רמב"ם, Rambam, and then he says and then comes יעקב Yaakov and
he was מתקן מעריב mitakein Maariv and he was מתקן מעשר. mitakein
ma'aser. I forget if he says—there's a מחלוקת machlokes רמב"ם Rambam ראב"ד
Ra'avad whether to describe the מעשר ma'aser to יצחק Yitzchak or to
יעקב Yaakov because there's a basis for both. Anyway, so the רמב"ם
Rambam makes it sound, and then we got the תורה Torah and
we got all תרי"ג מצוות. taryag mitzvos. So the רמב"ם Rambam makes
it sound like actually, you know, these practices were part of what
became ultimately our הלכה, halacha, not that it all gets
deferred. מתן תורה Matan Torah and until then it's all but irrelevant.
So that's a very fascinating question how much we see prior to
מתן תורה Matan Torah as relevant, but there's also a difference between
talking about that in terms of ברית מילה Bris Milah which was
commanded by God to אברהם Avraham and this which is just a
practice that they were adopting. And that's the way the ערוך Aruch
reads the challenge: how can you assume from a practice that was
adopted that we can learn anything about הלכה? halacha? Yes, Charlie.
The גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין Sanhedrin uses the actions of אברהם Avraham
to derive נחלות. nachalot.
Yes, okay, well that's interesting, but that could be a reflection of
what was being practiced based on the ציווי. tzivoi.
Specifically it was that he inherited a half-sibling.
Yeah, well that's also an interesting question we're going to get to
in a minute. Yes. The ערוך Aruch was
11th century I believe or 10th century, it was a רבי נתן,
Rabbi Natan, right, I'm trying to remember if it was 10th or
11th century, what's a hundred years between friends. Anyway, it was written
by
somebody who was a student of the גאונים Geonim and in Rome
actually, so a lot of the identifying the words as having Greek
or Latin origins he actually does correctly because it's coming from Italy
and Rome, but I forget the exact biography of him, but it's
10th or 11th century and it's with a lot of גאוני geonic
material and the מהרש"א, Maharsha,
17th century, something like that.
The ערוך Aruch was published the way we have it now with
like three different layers of it, being a late 19th early 20th
century scholar.
Yes, yes, who does a whole right, right.
Next question: what does he mean by the and follow meaning
following legislated law.
Doesn't mean what's
like the
נביאים, Nevi'im, what's post-תורה Torah and in נ"ך Nach to the degree
that we can say something is a גילוי מילתא giluy milsa when
it's said in נ"ך, Nach, not that it's מחדש דבר mechadesh davor
but a גילוי מילתא, giluy milsa, that's after we're talking already about
legislated law. Okay, so let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, hold on let me just
try to read you see if I can find it in two
seconds, the רמב"ם Rambam I was referring to.
You have the מצות mitzvot of שמירת שבת shmirat shabbat before מתן
תורה Matan Torah as well. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Right.
Okay,
hold on.
Let me see just if I can רבינו נתן?
Rabbeinu Natan? Yes.
Let me see just very quickly if I can find it.
רבינו נתן? Rabbeinu Natan?
Okay.
Oh wait, not yet. All
right,
I'm not finding it, let's go on. I'll look for later. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבא תנא גמרי
מאברהם ולא גמרינן מיניה? Amar Rava tana gamri me'Avraham v'lo gamrina minei?
We
תנא tana learns from אברהם Avraham and you're telling me we can't
learn from אברהם? Avraham? Where does the תנא tana learn from אברהם?
Avraham? Because we
started talking about daytime and where the sun is and relating to
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it relates to תפילה, tefillah, it's an interesting,
right, it's not a very clear transition. Okay, דתניא detanya we taught
in the
ברייתא: Beraita: וביום השמיני ימול בשר ערלתו, u'bayom hashmini yimol b'sar orlato,
מלמד שכל היום כשר למילה. melamed shekol hayom kasher l'milah.
So the day of the eighth day you could do it any
time on the eighth day. אלא שזריזין מקדימין למצות, ella shezrizim makdimim
l'mitzvot,
but we know that the people that are zealous
are do מצות mitzvot earlier. Where do we learn it from? From
אברהם. Avraham. שנאמר וישכם אברהם בבוקר ויחבוש את חמורו, shene'emar vayashkem Avraham
baboker vayachavosh es chamoro,
that אברהם Avraham got up early in the morning. So therefore even
though you could do מילה milah the whole day, you should try
to do it earlier. So you see we can learn from אברהם.
Avraham. אלא אמר רבא רב יוסף הכא קשיא ליה. ella amar Rava
Rav Yosef hacha kashyei lei.
Here's what was bothering רב יוסף Rav Yosef when he said how
could we learn from אברהם. Avraham. דתנן ditnan
we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, he wasn't really bothered about learning
from אברהם, Avraham, he was bothered about the claim that מנחה mincha
starts right at noon or 12:01 because we teach in a משנה:
Mishnah: חל ערב פסחים להיות ערב שבת, chal erev pesachim lihyot erev
shabbos,
when ערב פסח erev pesach falls on ערב שבת, erev shabbos, right,
so you gotta start doing the קרבן פסח korban pesach very early
because you need time to roast it because you can't roast it
at night because פסח pesach itself, first day of פסח pesach is
שבת. shabbos. נשחט בשישה ומחצה, nishchat b'shisha u'mechetza, so the תמיד tamid
was shechted as early as possible in six and a half hours,
meaning at 12:30. וקרב בשבעה ומחצה v'karav b'shiva u'mechetza and then it
was all brought up because we've now learned about dismembering it and
flaying it and bringing it to the altar, and that happened at
seven and a half hours, at 1:30. So here you see the
earliest possible to do the תמיד tamid is 12:30. ונשחטיה מכי משחרו
כותלי? vinishtatei mikimah shacharu kolsyei? Why not shecht it from the time
the walls get black, from 12:01, that's when the sun starts moving
away from giving its light against the wall? So by the way,
I want to point out to you an amazing shift, because this
exactly is repeating the big two sort of paradigm and debate, or
I would say two models of תפילה. tefillah. תפילה כנגד אבות tefillah
k'neged avot and תפילה כנגד קרבנות. tefillah k'neged korbanot.
We're saying אברהם, Avraham, so the challenge of are we going to
learn from אברהם Avraham now takes on a very different meaning. Because
the point is, since when are you going to use the אבות
Avot model of תפילה? Tefilah? If it was based on the אבות,
Avot, then we could say, look, you know, the idea, if you
think about it, what's שחרית, Shachris, מנחה, Mincha, מעריב? Maariv? Three times
during the day. Beginning of the day, middle of the day, end
of the day. So that has nothing to do with קרבנות. Korbanot.
Not end of day. Morning, afternoon, night. Excuse me. That's right. Three
times a day you pray to God. Morning, afternoon, night. So if
that's your model, having nothing to do with קרבנות, Korbanot, what's afternoon?
Starting at 12:01. That's afternoon. But he says, since when are we
learning from the model of אבות? Avot? We should learn our תפילה
Tefilah from the model of קרבנות. Korbanot. And קרבנות Korbanot is 12:30,
not noon. Okay, so which model you're learning from, it's not that
we know that אברהם Avraham דאוונד davened at 12:01. But the model
of אבות Avot is morning, afternoon, and evening. And that would say
12:01. He's saying, how do you learn from that? How do you
base that תפילה, Tefilah, the times of תפילה Tefilah at least, should
be based on קרבנות Korbanot and that would tell you 12:30, not
12:01. Yes?
You're just saying you're trying to learn ברית מילה Briss Milah from
אברהם, Avraham, right? But then we revert to a פסוק, pasuk, right?
Which is the עקידה. Akeidah. So we learn ברית מילה Briss Milah
from אברהם, Avraham, right?
No, I'm not going...
no, we have the מובהק, Muvak,
בעצם היום הזה, Beyetzem hayom hazeh, which is the middle of the
day.
Fine. The point is not... but fine. Anyway, we're learning a basic
principle of זריזים Zrizim from אברהם. Avraham. Anyway, back to the גמרא.
Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says: Look, if you go by the
קרבנות Korbanot model of תפילה, Tefilah, it should be 12:30. That's when
you would bring the earliest you could bring the תמיד. Tamid. So
the גמרא Gemara says: מאי קושיא, Mai Kushya, why is that difficult?
ודילמא כותלי דבית המקדש בשית ומחצה משחרי
משום דלא מכווני טובי. Vedilma kotlei deBeit Hamikdash besheish umetzah mishchari mishum
delo mekhavnu tuvei. Maybe yes, you're right. Maybe the walls of the
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash didn't get dark till 12:30 because in theory
because they were... they were not exactly perpendicular. So wait, no, the
רש"י Rashi explains it means that they were wider at the bottom
and narrower at the top. So the sun even when it passed
like overhead was still casting some light. I'm not a physicist, I
don't exactly get it. But apparently even if the sun is directly
overhead, it still casts some light on the wall if the wall's
at an
angle.
That's what רש"י Rashi says. Maybe somebody can explain that to me.
But if the walls... already our things are not working...
people don't put the caps on. If this is your wall and
the sun is here, right? So apparently some of the rays are
going to hit down on that side of the wall. Whereas if
your wall were straight towards the right, if your wall is straight,
then none of the rays hit this side of the wall once
it's directly overhead. Okay, so he's saying since the walls of the
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash looked like this, the walls were still light
until 12:30. Even after 12:01, the walls were still getting some sunlight.
And it was only when the sun had hit a little bit
more that the wall was actually dark. So what they're saying is:
No, really the הלכה Halacha is 12:01, but they just... but we
measure it... and this is also why it's relevant here, how do
you measure where the sun is? We measure it by looking at
the walls, and in the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, they didn't have...
it didn't seem to be the time yet based on the walls
until 12:30. What? I know. I don't know what to say about
that. Well, I will say something about that. Let's read a little
bit more. But in principle it's 12:01. Okay? אינמי, Inami, or you
could say, שאני אברהם דאצטגנינות גדולה היתה בלבו. Shani Avraham de-istagninus gedolah
hayetah belibo.
אברהם Avraham was a great astrologer and he was able to tell
exactly when it was 12:01. Us, the פשוטי עם, peshutei am, we
have to be safe and say 12:30. אינמי Inami משום דזקן ויושב
בישיבה הוא, mishum d'zaken veyoshev biyishiva hu,
or because he was a... so one is he was an astrologer
and the other... or he was like somebody that was a huge
תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham, he spent his time sitting in ישיבה yeshiva
and that gave him the wisdom to understand, the knowledge to understand
exactly when... exactly when it was 12:01, right? דאמר רבי חמא ברבי
חנינא מימיהם של אבותינו לא פרשה ישיבה מהם.
De'amar
Rabbi Chama bar
Rabbi Chanina, miyimeihem shel avoteinu lo parsha yeshiva mehem. From our...
there was never not ישיבה yeshiva learning from all of the time
of the forefathers. We were always learning תורה. Torah. היו במצרים ישיבה
עמהם. Hayu beMitzrayim, yeshiva imahem.
When they were in מצרים, Mitzrayim, there was literally... it means like
a ישיבה, yeshiva, but it pretty much means a ישיבה. yeshiva. It
means sitting and with elders, sitting and learning תורה. Torah. שנאמר, Shene'emar,
it says: לך ואספת את זקני ישראל. Lech ve'asafta et ziknei Yisrael.
So elders is understood here to mean not literally old, but sages.
היו במדבר ישיבה עמהם, Hayu bamidbar, yeshiva imahem, שנאמר: shene'emar: אספה לי
שבעים איש מזקני ישראל, esfa li shivim ish miziknei Yisrael, from the
sages. אברהם אבינו זקן ויושב בישיבה היה. Avraham Avinu zaken veyoshev biyishiva
hayah. אברהם Avraham was a sage sitting in a ישיבה. yeshiva. שנאמר:
Shene'emar: ואברהם זקן בא בימים. Ve-Avraham zaken ba bayamim. So the מהרש"א
Maharsha says: Why did we start with מצרים Mitzrayim and the מדבר
midbar and double back to אברהם? Avraham? He says because obviously when
it says about אברהם, Avraham, יצחק, Yitzchak, יעקב Yaakov being old, you
would think פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim is old. But once
we show that in מצרים Mitzrayim it says זקנים, zkenim, אספה לי
שבעים זקנים asfa li shivim zkenim and so on, clearly there you
don't just mean old people, you mean sages. So once you see
there you mean sages, so also we'll say that that's what it
means by
אברהם. Avraham. יצחק
אבינו זקן ויושב בישיבה שנאמר ויהי כי זקן יצחק, Yitzchak Avinu zaken
v'yosheiv b'yeshiva shene'emar vayehi ki zakein Yitzchak, יעקב אבינו זקן ויושב בישיבה
שנאמר ועיני ישראל כבדו מזקן, Yaakov Avinu zaken v'yosheiv b'yeshiva shene'emar ve'einei
Yisrael kavdu mizoken, אליעזר עבד אברהם זקן
ויושב בישיבה. Eliezer eved Avraham zaken v'yosheiv b'yeshiva. Okay, if
that's actually even fascinating because that's מזקן, mizoken, from old age, you
know? It's not that it doesn't even have the word זקן, zakein,
which you could say means an elder, a sage. There it says
from old age, but I guess it's, you know, that's what happens
when you read the small print of the רש"י Rashi and the
רמב"ן Ramban and בעל המאור, Ba'al HaMa'or, so your eyes get bad.
So already that was יעקב's, Yaakov that was יצחק's Yitzchak problem. Okay,
so anyway, I mean, I mean יעקב's Yaakov problems. Okay. אליעזר עבד
אברהם זקן ויושב בישיבה היה שנאמר ויאמר אברהם אל עבדו זקן ביתו
המשל בכל אשר לו Eliezer eved Avraham zaken v'yosheiv b'yeshiva haya shene'emar
vayomer Avraham el avdo zekan beito hamoshel b'kol asher lo that had
dominion over all that was his. So what does this mean? Now
we're going to reinforce this idea of being sitting and learning. אמר
רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, שמושל בתורת רבו. shemoshel b'toras rabbo. Interesting,
רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. He had keyed, had mastery over everything his
master taught him. So the מהרש"א Maharsha says the reason we have
to say that is, look, if he's not allowed to פסקן pasken
in the presence of אברהם, Avraham, how could he teach in the
presence of אברהם? Avraham? אברהם Avraham was his רבי מובהק. Rebbe Muvhak.
Ah, it must be he wasn't teaching his own תורה, Torah, he
was only teaching all the תורה Torah that he learned from אברהם.
Avraham. הוא דמשק אליעזר. Hu Damasek Eliezer. He is אליעזר Eliezer of
דמשק. Damascus. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, again interesting, אלעזר לאזר,
Elazar Lazar, שדולה ומשקה מתורתו של רבו לאחרים. shedoleh umashkeh mitoraso shel
rabbo l'acherim. So דמשק Damasek is like an acronym: דולה ומשקה. doleh
umashkeh. He would draw up the water and water, you know, and
provide the water of, so he draws from the wells of his
master and you know, and water for, provide the water for others.
It's actually also an interesting story because who else was דולה ומשקה?
doleh umashkeh? Right, that was when עבד אברהם Eved Avraham went, right,
and then רבקה, Rivka, right, was דולה ומשקה, doleh umashkeh, she drew
the water for the camels. So here he's drawing the water of
the תורה Torah for others. Right. Anyway, so the מהרש"א Maharsha says
part of the, part of the hint to this is that we
normally give the names after the person, like you know, יפתח הגלעדי.
Yiftach HaGiladi. So here דמשק אליעזר, Damasek Eliezer, so that gives them
a little license, they probably would have had the license anyway. So
anyway, now we're going to get on to, now that we're talking
about the אבות Avot being תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim and ראשי ישיבה,
Rashei Yeshiva, we're going to get on with that theme, but I
want to say one final thing about the time of דאוונען. davenen.
So the simple answer the גמרא Gemara makes it sound like, technically
you're right it's 12:01, but you know, we play it safe, they
didn't exactly weren't able to tell the time so well in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash as probably the תנאים Tanna'im here. So according
to that, maybe technically you could דאוונען davenen at 12:01. Okay, but
actually there are some opinions that say that no, that really the
reason the walls were wide in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash or
the reason they chose to go by that time was because it's
not exactly one minute after noon. To be considered the afternoon, you
know, when the sun is at the height, from like 11:30 to
12:30, the גמרא Gemara discusses this in פסחים, Pesachim, right about telling
what time it is and when you have to burn your חמץ
chametz or whatever. You know, it's like technically it might be 12:01,
but it's midday. It's not afternoon. Afternoon, and now we have watches,
12:01 is afternoon. But no, that's a different period, that's midday when
it's at the apex, like for the half hour before and
after. 12:31 and on, that's already afternoon. And that's an interesting question
about like בדיעבד, b'diavad, you know, מנחה Mincha from 12:01. It also
is interesting to discuss whether the גמרא's Gemara here just saying they
played it safe or really is claiming it was different and maybe
it's actually claiming again different models. Maybe it's claiming like אברהם's Avraham
model would be 12:01, you know, and the בית המקדש's Beit HaMikdash
model would be 12:30, not again a playing it safe but a
conceptual different model. So again, what is interesting about this is, you
know, is as I think, a playing out of the two models
of כנגד אבות k'neged Avot and כנגד קרבנות, k'neged Korbanot, as seeing
like which one do we learn in terms of the times from
and how exactly do you define when is the afternoon? It's a
bit of a מחלוקת. machloket. Okay, so now let's take a look.
אמר רב, Amar Rav, so now we've gotten to this digression here,
or this point about the, all of the אבות Avot being ראשי
ישיבה. Rashei Yeshiva. So אמר רב, Amar Rav, קיים אברהם אבינו כל
התורה כולה. kiyam Avraham Avinu kol haTorah kullah.
אברהם Avraham fulfilled the whole תורה. Torah.
שנאמר עקב אשר שמע אברהם בקולי. shene'emar eikev asher shama Avraham b'koli.
And it's really the end of the פסוק, pasuk, וישמור משמרתי מצותי
חוקותי ותורותי. vayishmor mishmarti mitzvotai chukotai v'torotai. חוקותי, Chukotai, what is it?
עקב אשר שמע אברהם בקולי
וישמור משמרתי מצותי חוקותי
ותורותי.
eikev asher
shama
Avraham b'koli vayishmor mishmarti mitzvotai chukotai v'torotai.
So all of that stuff, that's a lot of stuff. So מצות,
mitzvot, חוקים, chukim, תורות, Torot, that's כל התורה כולה. kol haTorah kullah.
Okay, what else is there? I mean, what? שבע מצות? Sheva mitzvot?
That's exactly, so that's what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר ליה שימי
בר חייא לרב, Amar leh Shimi bar Chiya l'Rav, ואימא שבע
מצות? v'eima sheva mitzvot? Maybe it just means he kept the seven
מצות. mitzvot. No, האיכא נמי מילה. ha'ika nami milah. The גמרא Gemara
says, one minute, האיכא נמי מילה. ha'ika nami milah. What do you
mean שבע מצות? sheva mitzvot? There was also מילה. milah. Okay, fine,
ואימא שבע מצות ומילה, v'eima sheva mitzvot u'milah, but maybe that פסוק
pasuk just means the seven מצות mitzvot and מילה. milah. אמר ליה,
Amar leh, אם כן, im kein, מצותי ותורותי למה לי? mitzvotai v'torotai
lama li? Meaning, come on, the פסוק pasuk is saying חוקותי, chukotai,
מצותי, mitzvotai, תורותי, torotai, it's not just שבע מצות, sheva mitzvot, that's
the whole shebang. So he kept כל התורה כולה. kol haTorah kullah.
Okay, so אמר רבא ואיתימא רב אשי, Amar Rava v'itayma Rav Ashi,
קיים אברהם. kiyam Avraham. Okay fine, and שבע מצוות ומילה, sheva mitzvos
u-mila, but maybe that פסוק passuk just means the שבע מצוות ומילה?
sheva mitzvos u-mila? אמר ליה, Amar lei, אם כן, im kein, מצותי
ותורותי mitzvosai ve-sorosai למה לי? lamma li? I mean come on, the
פסוק passuk is saying חקותי, chukosai, מצותי, mitzvosai, תורותי, torosai, it's not
just שבע מצוות. sheva mitzvos. It's the whole shebang. So he kept
כל התורה כולה. kol ha-Torah kula. Okay, so אמר רבא ואיתימא רב
אשי, amar Rava ve-isema Rav Ashi, קיים אברהם אבינו kiyem Avraham Avinu
אפילו עירובי תבשילין. afilu eruvei tavshilin. שנאמר Shene'emar תורותי. torosai. מאי תורות,
mai torot, my תורות torot in plural, אחת תורה שבכתב ואחת תורה
שבעל פה, achas Torah shebichtav ve-achas Torah sheba'al peh, whether it's the
written or the oral. Now, of course, that's a big חידוש chiddush
because even the idea of oral normally means the interpretation of the
written תורה Torah but still things that are biblical. עירובי תבשילין eruvei
tavshilin seems to have been specifically chosen to point out even something
that's purely rabbinic. This whole idea of עירובי תבשילין, eruvei tavshilin, you
know, from יום טוב Yom Tov going into שבת Shabbos is to
remind you not to forget about שבת Shabbos even if you're cooking
on יום טוב Yom Tov for שבת Shabbos and so on. That's
a completely rabbinic type of a thing. So to say אברהם Avraham
kept it is a pretty extreme statement. People try to give more
like symbolic explanations to why we're assigning עירוב תבשילין eiruv tavshilin to
אברהם Avraham like the מהרש"א Maharsha suggests the whole idea is about
remembering שבת Shabbos and keeping the מצוה mitzvah in mind. Anyway, it's
a very challenging גמרא Gemara in general, what this means that they
kept כל התורה כולה kol ha-Torah kula because as the רמב"ן Ramban
points out, they didn't keep כל התורה כולה. kol ha-Torah kula. יעקב
Yaakov married two sisters, you know, there's a lot of times they
had a מצבה, matzeiva, but you know later it says אשר שנא
ה' אלהיך asher sanei Hashem Elokecha but in the time of the
אבות Avot they had it. So the רמב"ן Ramban על התורה al
ha-Torah discusses, you know, whether we really should be taking this גמרא
Gemara literally or not, but it is this very famous idea that
the אבות Avot again, thinking about this, so not just the models
of
תפילה, tefillah, which is great, that's פשט הפסוקים, pshat ha-pesukim, they're the
models of what it means to speak to God, but then they
became the models of, you know, their status is also because they
were תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, and then it becomes זקן ויושב בישיבה,
zaken ve-yosheiv bi-yeshivah, we have to give them that identity, and then
we have to give them the identity of actually having done all
the מצוות, mitzvos, and it certainly puts that in juxtaposition with how
we read the beginning of the גמרא, Gemara, which was we can't
learn from that because that's pre-divinely legislated, again, that's the way you
read it, that becomes an interesting sort of dialectic between the beginning
and the end. Okay, so we'll pick up here on שבת. Shabbos.